Gladys Allen papers, Inclusive: 1882-1893, 1913-1952, undated, Bulk: 1941-1947
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Gladys Allen papers
Inclusive: 1882-1893, 1913-1952, undated, Bulk: 1941-1947
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
42
Allen, Gladys, 1897 - 1953
1 document box.
The Gladys Allen papers consists of materials accumulated by Gladys Allen, including correspondence, personal notes, genealogical research, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Gladys Allen was born 1897 June 2, in Crawford, Texas, to Sam L. Allen and Florence Morehead Allen. She attended Crawford public schools, Mary Hardin-Baylor College, and Baylor University (graduated 1918 June). Afterwards, she was the principal of the school at Delia, Texas, and later taught English in the Waco, Texas, school system. She taught in Waco until leaving to oversee business affairs for her father upon the death of her mother in 1934.
Allen was a member of the Baylor Board of Trustees from 1941-1947, and 1951-1953. During her time as a trustee, she was highly involved in Baylor’s re-admittance to the American Association of University Women (AAUW). When Baylor lost its AAUW status due to perceived gender inequalities, Allen (a member of the AAUW) conducted research which was influential to reclaiming the accreditation. In addition to being a trustee, she was a member of Seventh and James Baptist Church and taught Sunday school classes there from 1928-1947. Allen was also active in the Waco Garden Club and the Waco Garden Council. She also for a decade as president of the Waco Young Women’s Christian Association.
Allen died 1953 May 18 from cancer complications. She bequeathed assets to Seventh and James Baptist Church and Baylor University, including three endowed scholarships. Gladys Allen Hall at Baylor was named in her honor.
Scope and Content
The Gladys Allen papers date from 1882 to 1952, with most items ranging from 1941-1947. The papers include correspondence, materials related to Allen’s ancestry research and materials related to her time as a Baylor University trustee. Also included are wills of ancestors, organization applications, newspaper clippings, personal notes, photographs, artifacts from relatives, and other items collected by Allen.
Arrangement
The Gladys Allen papers were previously arranged in four series: Correspondence, Genealogical Materials, Baylor University Board of Trustees Materials, and Miscellanea. It was not clear if this arrangement was original order or imposed by an archivist upon accession. To enhance access, Miscellanea was expanded into two series, Literary Productions and Photographs.
Currently the Gladys Allen papers are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, II. Genealogical Materials, III. Baylor University Board of Trustees Materials, IV. Literary Productions, and V. Photographs.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 42. Acquired 1953-08-24
Related Resources
Related references
Kelley, Dayton, ed. The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County. Waco, TX: Texian Press, 1972.
Baylor University. “Allen Portrait To Be Revealed.” Baylor University press release, 1965 May 21.
“Gladys Allen Resigns at Fidelis Business Meeting” The Daily Lariat (Waco, TX), 1926 April 27.
Interview of Merle Mears McClellan Duncan. Baylor University Institute for Oral History, Waco, Texas. Accessed 31 May 2013.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.
Places
Waco (Tex.) -- History.
Subjects
Baptist universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; Genealogy.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1946-1950; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consists of letters to Gladys Allen while a trustee at Baylor University and president of the Waco Young Women’s Christian Association. Also included is a script for a 1946 KWTX radio broadcast involving Allen. This series is in good condition.
  - Correspondence and radio script, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Genealogical Materials, 1913-1945, undated; 2
  General condition: Average.
  This series consists chiefly of correspondence regarding Gladys Allen’s ancestry. Letters from family members and researchers are included in addition to Allen’s completed applications for the National Society for Daughters of the American Revolution, copies of John Allen’s will (recorded 1823, issued 1941), funeral proceedings for Sam Allen (1945), clippings of newspaper obituaries and a report titled “The Name and Family of Allen or Allan” prepared by the Media Research Bureau (issued in 1936). Personal notes are included on notecards and written on some of the items. This series is in average condition.
  - Correspondence and ancestry research, 1913-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Applications, wills, newspaper clippings, personal notes and other items, 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Baylor University Board of Trustees Materials, 1944-1947, undated; 3
  This series contains materials related to Baylor University’s loss of American Association of University Women accreditation, the bulk of which are responses to a 1944 survey of various institutions of higher education regarding gender equality and operational information. Also included are materials related to a 1947 Baylor University improvement program proposed by the current Baylor president Pat M. Neff. This series is in good condition.
  - American Association of University Women survey correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pat M. Neff improvement plan materials, 1945-1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Literary Productions, 1882-1893, 1945-1952, undated; 4
  This series consists of an assortment of items including personal notes (possibly genealogical related information), newspaper clippings, ephemera and two notebooks belonging to A. L. Allen chronicling agricultural and climate conditions in central Texas from 1882-1893. This series is in average condition.
  - Personal notes, newspaper clippings, ephemera and A. L. Allen notebooks, 1882-1893, 1945-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs, undated; 5
  This series contains a photograph of the Baylor University Board of Trustees and unidentified
  photographs found within the materials. This series is in average condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)